George Gordon, Lord Byron Collection
George Gordon, Lord Byron Collection
1812-1948
Byron, George Gordon Byron, Baron, 1788-1824
0.25 linear ft.
Variety of material associated with Lord Byron (letters, autograph, portraits, etc), and John S. Mayfield correspondence relating to a translation by Byron of Petrarch's "Death of Margo."
2458931
Biographical History
George Gordon Byron (1788-1824), 6th Baron of that name, better known simply as Lord Byron, was a noted English poet and leading figure in the Romantic movement. Among his best-known works are the poems "She walks in beauty" and "Childe Harold's Pilgrimage."
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The George Gordon, Lord Byron Collection comprises correspondence and writings of the English poet, as well as a small amount of miscellaneous material relating to him.
Correspondence / writings contains seven outgoing letters (recipients include Lorenzo Bartolini, John Hanson, Francis Hodgson, Thomas Moore, and John Murray), and two signed holograph manuscripts of the English poet (1788-1824). The manuscripts and three of the letters are bound in a full green morocco folio volume by Stikeman along with a cut autograph of Lord Byron, five engraved portraits, and an introduction to the collection by George S. Hellman.
Mayfield material contains correspondence and a clipping. The correspondence consists of incoming letters to book collector and librarian John S. Mayfield, relating to a translation by Byron of Petrarch's "Death of Margo." Correspondents include the Library of Congress, the University of Texas at Austin, Henry E. Huntington Library, Broughton High School in England, and others. Mayfield was evidently trying to trace the appearance of this 53-line piece by Byron in Ugo Foscolo's Essays on Petrarch (1823).
Miscellaneous consists of a bound volume containing a handwritten transcription of the third edition of Byron's English Bards and Scotch Reviewers. A Satire (1810). The date and author of the transcription is unknown, but it is complete from the title page to the poem at the end.
Arrangement of the Collection
Letters are chronological.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- British; Bartolini, Lorenzo, 1777-1850.; Byron, Catherine Gordon, 1764?-1811.; Byron, George Gordon Byron, Baron, 1788-1824.; Hanson, John.; Hellman, George S. (George Sidney), 1878-1958.; Hodgson, Francis, 1781-1852.; Mayfield, John S., 1904-1983.; Moore, Thomas, 1737 or 8-1823.; Murray, John Archibald Murray, Lord, 1778-1859.; Poets, English -- 19th century; Correspondence.; Poems.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Sol Feinstone
Inventory
- Correspondence / writings
  - Bound volume (Box 1)
    Contains the following:
    Letter, 1812 Aug. 31: "Dear Sir" [i.e. John Hanson]. Provenance: Ord family (former owner?); George S. Hellman (former owner); Frederick S. Peck (former owner); Sol Feinstone (donor). Published in Byron's Letters and Journals 2:189-190
    Letter, 1814 Jul. 8: "My dear Hodgson" [i.e. Francis Hodgson]. Provenance: Ord family (former owner?); George S. Hellman (former owner); Frederick S. Peck (former owner); Sol Feinstone (donor). Published in Byron's Letters and Journals 4:137-138
    Letter, 1814 Jul. 11: "My dear Hn." [i.e. Francis Hodgson]. Provenance: Ord family (former owner?); George S. Hellman (former owner); Frederick S. Peck (former owner); Sol Feinstone (donor). Published in Byron's Letters and Journals 4:139
    Manuscript, "An Edinburgh eclogue". Autograph manuscript signed "N.G.B. [Noel Gordon Byron]" [3] p. Attributed to Lord Byron by George S. Hellman, 1916.--cf. "Notes concerning the preceding unpublished manuscripts of Lord Byron" bound with mss. Provenance: Ord family (former owner?); George S. Hellman (former owner); Frederick S. Peck (former owner); Sol Feinstone (donor)
    Manuscript, "A meeting sadder than a parting". Autograph manuscript signed "N.G.B. [Noel Gordon Byron]" [2] p. Attributed to Lord Byron by George S. Hellman, 1916.--cf. "Notes concerning the preceding unpublished manuscripts of Lord Byron" bound with mss. Provenance: Ord family (former owner?); George S. Hellman (former owner); Frederick S. Peck (former owner); Sol Feinstone (donor)
    Also, five engraved portraits, typescripts of all manuscripts, and George S. Hellman's "Notes concerning the preceding unpublished manuscripts of Lord Byron". Cut autograph of Lord Byron also laid-in.
  - "Dear Sir [i.e. _____ Corbet]", 1813 Mar. 5 (Box 1)
    Published in Byron's Letters and Journals 3:24
    Sol Feinstone (donor)
  - "Dear Sir [i.e. John Murray]", 1817 Jun. 18 (Box 1)
    Published in Byron's Letters and Journals 5:241-242
    Provenance: Sol Feinstone (donor)
  - "Signore [i.e. Lorenzo Bartolini]", 1821 Nov. 10 (Box 1)
    Published in Byron's Letters and Journals 9:57-58
  - ["To Thomas Moore"], undated (Box 1)
    fragment
- Mayfield material
  - Correspondence, 1947-1948; relating to Byron's translation of Petrarch's "Death of Margo" (Box 1)
  - Clipping, 1969; short piece by Mayfield, "Byron's Vampyre Letter" (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Catherine Byron letters, 1794; 1825; to "My Dear Madam [Leigh]" and W. W. Horton, includes letter from Leslie Marchand to Mayfield regarding the letters from Catherine (Box 1)
  - Manuscript transcript of Byron's English Bards and Scotch Reviewers. A Satire, bound volume containing handwritten transcription of the third edition, published in 1810 (Box 1)